Just an extraordinary thinker. Someone who continually reminded me that there was
another way of doing things, there was another way of thinking.
Things didn't have to be thought this way. He questioned everything.
Roy Landau used to say that he'd question the most fixed assumptions in everyone
else's minds
and almost mischievously go for the thing which was obviously unquestionable and
questioned it.
And it was lovely. Kept you alert.
He was a sort of very sympathetic person. I mean, he cared about people.
I mean, one of his tests when you went to the office for an interview apparently was
he'd ask you to do a drawing as an architect, but what he asked you to do was to
draw two
escalators, one going up and one going down.
And you had to make it clear which was which without resorting to anything obvious
like
a sign or an arrow.
It was very simple.
You obviously put people on them.
But if you didn't put people on, he'd say, you know, you're not an architect.
You're not interested in people first and the escalator second.
And it was a, this story may even be anecdotal, but it would be typical of Cedric.
People first.
And he really did care.
And as a result, he wasn't really gentle with people who didn't.
I think one of the most lovely things about Cedric was his sense of time.
He was fascinated by time.
He could always finish his lectures to the minute.
He really cared about this.
and when he, during this period when he was this permanent critic to my unit,
this is around about the very end of the 80s, let's say 89,
Cedric and I were holding seminars on my yacht in St Catherine's Dock
very early every Friday morning,
which was a kind of revenge on the students for the fact they never turned up for
things on time.
We had these meetings, I think they started at either 7 or 8,
and there was champagne and caviar and smoked salmon
for those who got there on time.
And they were fed and each of us in turn brought a guest for breakfast.
And we brought every distinguished architect you can think of
plus a very eclectic mixture of politicians, left-wing unionists,
Tory peers, a whole range of people came to the yacht for that.
And it's all recorded in the logbook.
At the end of the year, Cedric knew we were going to sail back to Ireland.
And he asked rather casually what time high tide was.
It was about 5am.
The following morning, 5am, there is Cedric at the lock gates.
Because Cedric of course knew that the only time he could get out was when the high
tide, when the lock gates could open.
and I thought it was a lovely story because it first of all showed his fixation with
time and his interest in that
but also that he would bother.
Couldn't he say goodbye the day before in the evening?
No, he had to come down to the, especially at five o'clock in the morning
which can't have been that convenient even for Cedric
and say goodbye.
I mean, lovely.
I mean, that kind of care, it's both compassion and care and consideration and
timing.
Perfect.
I got a call one morning on the telephone, I think it was Christmas Eve,
and it was Nick Bailey on the phone, in fact.
Nick was one of my students at Cambridge.
Nick was working for Cedric at the time on the generator, it turned out,
which I'd never heard at the time, saying,
John, we need your help, and the story unfolded from there.
Nick sent me, or Cedric, the following morning for Christmas present,
this great wad of drawings appeared, which always made me laugh
because nowhere did it say what the site was.
But the shadow projections were so accurate that I was able to work out it must be
the latitude of Florida.
Which tells you another thing about Cedric and accuracy and timing and so on.
And also Nick, of course, is my student, so I knew it would be right, wouldn't it,
Nick?
And the brief then was, could you write a computer program which would configure the
site
in response to the changing needs of the client.
And these all had strange names,
like the rector, or I can't remember the names of the factor,
these people working on the site.
The answer to that was yes.
We had a Tektronix 4051,
which I had managed to persuade the University of Elstertum by,
for me, as a kind of dowry,
to persuade me to go there.
This must be the end of 1978.
And we did just that. We wrote this software that enabled you to plan and replan the
site in response to changing requirements.
So you put those in from forms which CEDTRIQ had already been circulating to the
staff.
And from that, the computer program would rework this out and plot it.
We had the most sophisticated computing system in any university, in the Department
of Architecture at that point,
which I had persuaded the then rector of the university there to buy as my diary.
It was immensely expensive and we were probably the only people who could have
possibly done this for Cedric and so we wrote the software for him and
generated all these drawings. Now some interesting things about this, one of
which was Cedric never ever came to see the computer working nor did he
ever touch it himself but he sent Ron Heron and Ron Heron found this immensely
amusing because there's Ron with Archigram and you think all this
computer stuff, but a bit of it. Ron had never actually touched a computer in his
life at this
point. Oh, Ron sits down there and thinks he's this great, but he'd only draw
Cedric. And we
had this problem explaining to Ron that's because we'd programmed it. He said, well,
could you program it to draw Ron Herro? And I said, well, no, that's another
project.
And that was all wonderful. And then we, so we wrote this program for him that did
everything
he wanted. And then we had a little think about this and Julia and I, my wife was
the
partner working on this project, she did most of the programming, I did most of the
systems design.
We decided that the problem, one of the problems was you'd never know whether the
crane driver
had moved the parts to the right place and how would the program know where. So at
that point,
this was 1978, at that point,
the very first microprocessor-based computer chips
appeared on the market.
One of them was in this Tektronix 4051 we had.
So we had one of the very first ever into England.
Well, actually, it was Ireland.
And he said, right, we'll embed one of those
in every single part of the building
so the building is literally intelligent and knows where it is.
And to prove this, we built a model, a physical model,
which is a red gridded board which is now in the Museum of Modern Art and each cell
of this
represented one cell of the building and that contained every single part contained
a computer
chip and these computers communicated with each other and they drove a plotter which
then drew
the overall configuration of the site but then they became the controlling computer
and they
talked to each other and decided how to best configure the site so the building
became quite
literally intelligent, a phrase which Dan Sudjik picked up in the, I think it was
the RIBA journal
at the time. Anyhow, the point about this was that there was too much computing
power. So what do you
do when you've got too much brain power? Well, you get bored. So we thought, right,
the system can get
bored with itself and start making arbitrary suggestions. And this is not facetious
because
the point about that was it would provoke people to make changes. If a cell of the
building got
bored with where it was and sent instructions to the crane driver to move it, the
crane driver
would never know why, whether this is because the cell was bored or because there
was some real need.
But the result of doing this is they would provoke a chain reaction. So first of
all,
people get used to changing buildings. Secondly, that on the basis of these
arbitrary changes,
there would be feedback so it could start to learn.
And that was the most important thing.
Not that the building was intelligent,
but the building was intelligent enough to learn from the response to people
how to better rearrange itself.
With some sort of idealistic vision that maybe in the end
it would get better at organising itself
than we might be able to organise it, having set this process in.
So we built this working model.
And I flew over to London with it to show Cedric,
and he was so excited.
because we couldn't carry the computer,
so he went and hired a Commodore PET,
personal electronic transactor.
That's what we had before PCs.
Personal electronic trans...
And he hired one at the top of the call road.
And there it was in his office,
and he was expecting massive hassles settling out.
He said, no, no, no, Cedric,
it's going to take me ten minutes to wire this up.
So he said, well, have a brandy.
So they were dreaming.
And we plug all this together, and it worked.
Lo and behold.
And there Cedric...
Absolutely.
I've never seen Cedric totally gobsmacked
As he found he could move this model around, as he moved it around, the computer
screen changed
and it produced perspectives of each of the permutations as fast as he could change
it.
And that was the only time I ever saw Cedric touch anything remotely like a computer
himself.
But he loved it.
And that was how we came to make the generator, or propose that the generator should
be intelligent.
This is exactly what he said in Building Design, January 1979.
Just to add to the computer and architecture debate,
I include this proposal from my consultants
on our latest project in which this friendly machine is widely used.
Oh yes, the site and the elements on it
should have a life and intelligence of their own
and the programme would start to generate unsolicited plans,
improvements and modifications
in response to users, comments, records of activity,
or even by building in a boredom concept,
so the site itself starts to make proposals
about changes of itself if no changes are made.
Now, such a proposal can only work
if the initial design allows layouts and structures
that can alter and decay and disappear.
Mine can, et cetera.
So he got it, he understood it,
He wrote about it. That's enough.
Monica Pidgeon published a series of audio tapes about projects at the time,
and one was The Generator.
And he prefaces it.
The first slide that comes up is,
technology is the answer, but what was the question?
And I think this was right,
that Sedgwick realised how very, very powerful the computer could be,
but how it wasn't going quite in the direction it ought to.
You asked me a moment ago about Cedric's understanding of computers and the attitude
of the technology. I make two observations about that. One is specifically about the
computer, the other is about technology in general. The example I made a note about
here,
which I'll read because it will make it clearer for me, which I wrote before, but
he said, whilst Cedric was always the first to understand the potential of a new
technology,
and I think that exactly describes it.
He was very technologically alert.
He was always producing clippings from the journals about technology.
He was far too sensible to actually use it.
He left that to others.
Hence, no voice messages.
He didn't have a tape in his voice machine.
He didn't want to waste the morning dealing with yesterday's problems, as he put it.
And also, he had no fax machine,
although later I discovered he did, but it had no paper in it for the same reason.
No word processor, no computer drafting.
So technology could be just a thought experiment
and what we came to describe later as computing without computers.
And the other observation about this later, when he was teaching with me,
I picked up the brief on the way here for a project he set in 1990 with me.
and Cedric participated in one of a series of introductory exercises called Choice
with my AA diploma students.
The brief began with a quote from Cedric.
Taking infinite pains with a problem is best left to the computer.
Making a choice is the human's role.
This exercise will test your thinking so far by looking at the generator project.
you'll be required to hypothesise rules and procedures for organising the generator
and
simulate the results with models. Propose how the computer might be useful or
otherwise,
but try to refrain from using it. Cedric's sense of humour was an absolute delight
to those of us
who were on his wavelength. His humour was magic. It was that beautiful, dry, wry
English humour.
where sometimes you didn't even realise he'd made a joke until a split second later.
The danger with this is it doesn't transfer well to other cultures.
It doesn't translate.
In fact, it really makes some people very angry
because they confuse it with sarcasm,
or they think it's akin to irony,
and that's greatly hated, particularly in America,
and particularly into cultures where it won't work,
like many Asian cultures.
you just can't translate ironic humour.
So I think that Cedric may have also been the victim of his humour
in the sense that I suspect a large number of people
either couldn't understand what he was talking about
or misunderstood it or maybe were even angered by it.
And that may be part of the reason why he's such an enigma
and doesn't have a higher international regard as he might have,
particularly in America.
I think the iconic Cedric project has to be the first major project in the Fun
Palace.
For several reasons. First, it was early, of course.
Secondly, it has a cute name.
Thirdly, it somehow was the first building to ever embody critical ideas about
flexibility, interaction,
the idea that the people using the building could control it,
that it might need some cybernetic system indeed to control it.
When the press wanted drawings and things, there were no elevations.
They finally got a kind of helicopter view of it at night
with this sort of structural skeleton which explained almost nothing.
And then there were some enigmatic little diagrams
with captions sort of like west elevation, north elevation.
They said movement, flow, direction.
and it was all in black and white and cut out.
This all came from the impresario,
Joan Littlewood, the theatre impresario,
and she was a friend of Gordon Pask's, the cybernetician,
because he had an interest in theatre.
And the other reason it has to be the most important
and earliest building is that it was so obviously copied.
and the most obvious one being the Pompidou Center where a lot of the notion of the
big spaces the
intended flexibility were there and the original competition proposals had a lot
more flexibility
and moving parts than ever finally constructed so yes wonderful to see it but sad it
was kind
of monumental eyes I mean I love Richard Rogers and I love the Pompidou Center but
on the other
hand it kind of, by monumentalising the Fun Palace, it killed it. There was no real
interaction
there, there is no real flexibility, but it's obviously a very different kind of
exhibition
space and it looks very different and everyone remembers it because all those pipes
on the
outside. It gained notoriety and interest for the wrong reasons and, that's my point
there and distracted interest from the flexibility and potential of a very different
kind of
gallery which is what the underlying concept of the Fun Palace was. And that
building I've
seen it again and again and again and again, acknowledged or otherwise ideas. Some
cases
students don't even know where the ideas have come from because somehow we don't
have a
a very good history of the immediate past. I love the Potteries Thinkbelt project
because
it rethinks what universities might be and addressed really serious social issues in
the central area of Britain which had been the potteries and which had been totally
destroyed
by rises in automation of pottery fabrication. The university gathers monastic-like
groups
round the only really valuable resource which is rare old books. And 800 years ago
this
made a lot of sense because all books were rare and precious and these centres of
knowledge
and those monks who looked after them in these orders who had the discipline to
discipline
the minds to study these works made some kind of sense 800 years ago perhaps. But
now what
kind of sense does that make? We don't need central libraries anymore and
universities.
We don't need lectures anymore in the sense of everyone sitting around and being
pontificated
to by some professor like me. It's a nonsense. So Cedric really addressed this issue
and
produced this proposal to use the railway network in an industrially running down
area
to connect people up, to make this open to people who had missed out on university
education,
an alternative if you like to the open university. And it was a kind of iconic
statement of how
architecture could address social issues. The problem was always raised that
Sedgwick was quite clearly interested in things being more than objects as
architecture, but how did this manifest itself? Well in this case it manifested
itself as a series of railway trucks which variously unfolded or whatever.
The project when looked at in detail doesn't actually make a great deal of
sense but no matter because it stands as an iconic idea of an alternative, a
flexible thing in a rundown area and architecture being the proactive force
of change to address these issues so I have a great interest. It's also the
project that he chose to show at the International Dialogue of Experimental
Architecture at Folkestone in 1966. This was a crucial year for me.
This conference in Folkestone was supposed to be a small, basically
archigram based type event in a little coastal town which Peter Cook loved
and it got totally out of hand. All over Europe thousands of architectural
students turned up so expecting an audience of 300 there were 3,000
sleeping on the beach. And there were the most fantastic talks and it was chaotic.
There
was light getting into the lecture theatre, you couldn't see Cedric's slides.
Archigram
got booed but nothing light to the extent that Claude Parra and Paul Virilio with
their
architecture pranquit, they were just shouted off the stage and booed because they
were
seen as being neo-fascist. The atmosphere was fabulous. It was all happening at
night
on the beaches with everyone talking and exchanging ideas in a way which I had never
seen before.
And that is when I first heard Cedric talk about the Finkbelts Proterites and I
thought,
my god, this scheme is the most revolutionary project of everything we've seen in
this mind-blowing
conference. He used to turn up to schools of architecture conferences and things,
which
It's just been very dull for him, but I think he saw this as part of his duty.
He had something called polyarch.
In those days, the polytechnics were differentiated from universities,
and the polytechnics, the schools of architecture, were so boring.
The projects were boring, the staff were boring.
They were frustrated by the...
The students and the staff were frustrated by the projects
and the principals of the colleges,
who were generally career administrators
rather than enlightened and charismatic academics
or charismatic professional architects.
And he set up this thing called PolyArch.
The idea was to travel around and try and help some of these destitute.
And of course the schools thought of this as gross arrogance on Cedric's part
and the students absolutely adored it.
And after it became a little bit politically problematic
to actually go to the universities,
I'm thinking of the Cedric Price Memorial event where Rem and I both spoke.
Rem and I had a bit of a frosty relationship previously, but of course we shook
hands,
and polite as one does on such occasions, but Rem said he couldn't stay for my
piece.
So he went first, and he really was quite generous about Cedric,
And you could see that Cedric was a real nudge to his conscience.
When Peter Cook described Cedric as the conscience of us all, you could see this was
troublesome
to Rem.
And Rem had to kind of nail this, so he talked about the Tensegrity cage, the bird
cage,
and the only thing, but it was still a cage.
That was sort of Rem coping with it.
And then I talked and I had, because you imagine quite a different spin on all this,
and Rem
stayed and Rem came up afterwards and we shook hands properly and we both said we
respected
what each other had said.
But I think that is a sort of indicator of the problem that those with a formal
preoccupation
have.
And Rem would like to think he's more than that and beyond that, I'm sure.
But it keeps on manifesting itself in such formal ways.
Whereas with Cedric, the form never gets in the way.
It's all to do, the process is so visible,
to the extent that sometimes nothing got built at all.
Roy was a close friend of Cedric's, and Roy was my third-year tutor,
and I knew them both very well.
They knew each other very well and dined together frequently at the Gay Hussar.
And the way Roy put it was, the questioning of indisputable premises.
Another quote from Cedric himself was that architecture should have little to do
with problem solving.
Rather, it should create desirable conditions and opportunities, hitherto thought
impossible.
I like that. There's no point in asking for the brief because how would anyone know
what they would want?
He's going to offer them something they didn't know they could have.
And actually, I've only just been to see the Tugendhat house in Bruno, the Mies
building.
And Mies said an almost extraordinarily similar thing to his clients.
And I thought to myself, I could have imagined that Mies and Cedric might have
something in common.
And then I remembered the cigars.
I'm not being silly. There's something about the way they sat and the photographs of
them.
There's one picture of Mies exhaling cigar smoke in the book I've just got,
and there's one of Cedric, and they could be transposable.
Maybe smoking cigars does something to the...
Anyway, Price was the most provocative questioner of the architectural profession
and its assumptions, rejecting traditional architectural conventions and values,
challenging the social, functional, aesthetic norms.
Price was extremely highly regarded and acknowledged by the leading architectural
thinkers of the time but remained an enigma to the rest of a sleepy profession, as
Cedric called it.
The catalogue of projects from his small practice is immense in quantity as well as
the quality of
their thinking but most of all was his staggering ability to think the unimaginable.
His projects
are recognised as the seminal architectural propositions of the 20th century.
I'm quoting myself here from a book called The New Makers of Modern Culture.
If you don't know this book, it's rather special
because it's not an encyclopaedia of the great worthies of the 20th century.
Everyone being invited to make a contribution,
it wasn't confirmed that you would make the contribution
until you wrote explaining why they were a maker of modern culture.
That is, it was no good just to have been important,
because you can think of any number of architects who didn't get into the book.
Now, Cedric got in because I made the case that he was a contributor,
in the sense that he made aspects of culture in the 20th century.
And I think that's absolutely true.
And that's why I think his reputation will survive, because he was a maker of modern
culture.
His ability to rethink every issue, to approach everything fresh, to approach
everything as if it had never been thought about before,
but at the same time respecting history and previous ideas.
Cedric's library is of great interest. Eleanor Bronn and Sam Harding published after
his death
a complete catalogue to the library and seeing the eclecticism and the Catholicism
of that reading,
including eight copies no less of the Pickwick papers, really starts to give
insights into
Cedric's thinking, his humanitarianism, his breadth of scientific architectural
research
and his basic delving into the making of culture as we understand it.
The fundamental concepts of the generator and the fun palace and the Potteries
Thinkbelt
are models of a future architecture as yet unrealised.
These are not so much projects but generic ideas about new ways of making
environments
responsive to the needs and desires of their users.
They represent a fundamental archetype of a new deal for users, or a new menu in
Cedric's terminology.
The generator still has much to say to those who believe that architecture should
serve the users,
and a new model might speak to a new generation who might yet realise the future of
which Cedric has given us a vision.